A precious psalm this is, and many of us are familiar with this psalm, and we've looked
at it various times throughout the years, and we've been blessed by it.
And I really just want to start dealing with the psalm in verse number 7 this evening.
I'm going to read the verses, we'll get right into the message.
Psalm 19, beginning in verse number 7.
The Bible says this, the law of the Lord is perfect, converting the soul.
The testimony of the Lord is sure, making wise the simple.
The statutes of the Lord are right, rejoicing the heart.
The commandment of the Lord is pure, enlightening the eyes.
The fear of the Lord is clean, enduring forever.
The judgments of the Lord are true and righteous altogether.
More to be desired are they than gold.
Notice what it says, yea, than much fine gold.
Sweeter also than honey and the honeycomb.
Moreover by them is thy servant warned, and in keeping of them there is great reward.
Who can understand his errors?
Cleanse thou me from secret faults.
Keep back thy servant also from presumptuous sins.
Let them not have dominion over me.
Then shall I be upright, and I shall be innocent from the great transgression.
Let the words of my mouth and the meditation of my heart be acceptable in thy sight, O
Lord, my strength and my Redeemer.
As we look at this portion of scripture this evening, I've simply titled the message
The Law of the Lord, and we'll look at these verses of scripture, but we understand as
a Bible-believing church, we talk much about the Bible.
In fact, we would say as Baptists that we declare that the Bible is the sole authority
for faith and practice.
We stand upon that, and we rejoice in the truth that we have a Bible.
In fact, we sing songs about the Bible.
And one of the little songs that we sing in Sunday school in junior church, and we've
taught it to our grandchildren, the B-I-B-L-E, yes, that's the book for me.
Amen?
Aren't you thankful to have a Bible?
I stand alone on the word of God, the B-I-B-L-E, and I'm thankful.
Wonderful words of life, sing them over again to me, and we think about these wonderful
songs and just the fact that we have a Bible, and we're thankful, and we stand up and we
declare.
It is the sole authority for our faith and practice.
And I would say all these things are good, and right, and proper.
However, I believe this evening that the reality is that you can go to a Bible-believing
church, claim to be a Baptist, sing songs about the Bible, and yet spend very little
time reading, studying, and applying the word of God personally in your life.
I'm thankful we have the right Bible.
I'm thankful we have a Bible.
I'm thankful that we can sing about, preach about, talk about the Bible.
And I want you to understand that it's absolutely imperative that the word of God that we say
that we believe, that we stand upon, that we sing about, that we would declare to others
maybe that would talk about various things with regard to tradition and other things.
No, no, no, the Bible, the Bible, the Bible.
But we need to be careful that the Bible doesn't just become something that we talk about and
not something that we spend time just feasting upon the manna of God's word.
We find that the psalmist did not have the complete revelation of God.
How many of you are thankful to have the whole Bible this evening?
Amen.
I mean, we don't just have a part of it.
We don't just have sections of it.
We don't just have a New Testament.
You know, we send Bibles all around the world with Beacon of Truth Baptist Ministries.
And at times, some of those places, they only get John.
Maybe sometimes they get Romans.
Maybe John and Romans.
Sometimes they just get a New Testament.
But we have the whole canon of Scripture, the whole Bible.
What a blessing.
And we think about the truth that the psalmist did not have the complete revelation of God.
And yet we understand that the psalmist loved the Bible, loved the word of God.
And we find that as you study through the Psalms that his love for the Scriptures is
clearly understood.
It's declared plainly.
But then we understand that not only, listen, it's fine for us to say, I love the Bible.
But if you love the Bible, then you're going to meditate upon it.
You're going to spend time with God's word.
You're going to apply God's word.
And you're going to understand that there is evidence of your love for the word of God.
And we find that the psalmist loved the word of God, which resulted in reading, memorizing,
declaring, and applying the Scriptures in his own life.
And for us this evening, as we look at this portion of Scripture, I hope, again, a familiar
passage, but one in which we'll look afresh this evening and trust God to give us something
that would help us.
If you're taking notes, number one, the word of God is described.
Beginning in verse number seven and down through verse number nine, God gives us some description
about the Bible, the word of God.
And again, we understand that we now have the whole canon of Scripture.
But I want you to notice as you go through these few verses of Scripture that God reveals
to us what the Scripture is called.
He then describes it for us.
And then he tells us what it does.
See, the Bible tells us in 2 Timothy 3 and verse number 16, for all Scripture is given
by inspiration of God and is profitable.
See, before the apostle Paul wrote those words, he tells his son of the faith, Timothy, but
continue thou.
Now remember, before he even tells him to continue, he says that evil men and seducers
shall wax worse and worse, deceiving and being deceived.
But continue thou in the things which thou hast learned and been assured of, knowing
of whom thou hast learned them, and that from a child thou hast known the holy Scriptures,
which are able to make thee, notice what it says, wise unto salvation.
Praise God for the Bible.
And it is profitable.
And in these few verses of Scripture, we see that the writer, of course all Scripture
is given by inspiration of God, but God reveals to us these terms by which the Scriptures
are referred to and how it's described and what it does for us.
And notice he says in verse number 7, the law of the Lord.
The law of the Lord.
The Torah would be in focus, no doubt, for the Jewish believers or the Jewish people
at this particular time of the writing.
But I want you to see what he says about the law of the Lord.
He says it's perfect.
Now I am thankful that the Bible is without error, amen?
Man is fallible, but God is infallible.
And we talk about the fact that our Bible is inerrant.
It is not possible of having errors.
Why?
Because it is given to us by a God who is perfect.
And he's given to us a perfect book.
The word also carries with it the idea of complete.
And I'm thankful that for us now today, remember that Paul would say this in 1 Corinthians
13, that that which is in part is come.
He says it's gonna be done away with when that which is perfect is come, then that which
is in part is done away with.
And we find that God has given to us the whole canon of Scripture.
The law of the Lord, he says is perfect.
And notice it says there in verse 7, converting the soul.
I wonder this evening, have you been converted?
What does it mean to be converted?
Well, you've been born again, amen?
And we understand the truth of conversion.
The Bible tells us, Peter says that we're not born again with corruptible seed.
No, by that which is incorruptible by the word of God, which liveth and abideth forever.
And I wonder this evening, are you sure of heaven?
Have you trusted the Lord Jesus Christ as your personal Savior?
As I mentioned a moment ago from 2 Timothy 3 and verse 15, it's the Scriptures that Timothy
knew from a child that were able to make him wise unto salvation.
We find that without a Bible, you wouldn't know that you had sin.
Without a Bible, you wouldn't know about the Savior, and you wouldn't know about the plan
of redemption.
You wouldn't understand the truth of why Jesus went to the cross of Calvary and shed his
precious blood, not for his own sin because he was sinless, but for the sin of humanity.
Why?
Because he loved us.
And we begin to understand the Scriptures and how thankful we are for how God has provided
to us this truth in verse number seven.
He continues in verse number seven and says, the testimony of the Lord is sure.
Now he uses that phrase, the testimony of the Lord and what the Scriptures would be
called or referred to.
In the testimony of the Lord, that's the witnesses, if you will, and we find that he says that
it is sure, it is reliable, it is faithful.
I'm thankful this evening that we have a Bible that is, that is reliable.
That we can have confidence that this is God's Word.
That we can come and we can look, and again, you've often heard me say, and I don't mean
to take issue with individuals that would use different terminology, but I refrain and
work really hard to never refer to something in the Bible as a story, because it just carries
a context.
Listen, there are some stories that kids read that are just made up, and all of a sudden
they start hearing about the quote-unquote story of Jonah, and they...
equate it with the same thing, why?
Because they never heard about a man
getting swallowed by a whale.
You understand what I'm saying?
And he says that the testimony of the Lord is sure,
it's reliable, it's faithful.
One old preacher said this,
he was being questioned about believing the Bible.
He said, so you mean to tell me that you really believe
that a whale swallowed Jonah?
He said, I believe the Bible so much
that if the Bible told me that Jonah swallowed the whale,
I'd believe it, amen?
And praise God.
Listen, you may not, there may be some things,
listen, Peter said there's some things
that are hard to be understood.
There's milk of the word, there's meat of the word.
But God's word is reliable.
And we can rejoice in that, why?
Because he says that it's sure.
And then notice what he says, making wise the simple.
Oh, we need wisdom.
Wisdom comes from God, it comes from his word.
Making wise the simple.
He goes in verse number eight,
as he continues to describe the book
that you hold in your hands this evening,
the statutes of the Lord.
I would refer to the precepts of the Lord,
Notice what he says, are right.
God's word is always right.
And we live in a society today
that wants to call evil good and good evil,
and they wanna twist all kinds of things up.
But we just need to go back to the statutes of the Lord
because they're right.
The Bible says not only are they right,
but notice it says this in verse number eight,
rejoicing the heart.
Rejoicing the heart.
Listen, it's good to know that something is right
and we can stand upon it.
It's not my opinion or your opinion,
it's what the God of the universe said,
and he preserved it for us, he gave it to us,
and it rejoices the heart.
He says in verse number eight,
the commandment of the Lord.
Those are the directives that God gives.
We sang to start the service this evening,
trust and obey.
There are some commands in God's word.
By the way, I'm thankful for the commands that God gives us.
And he says here, he says in verse number eight,
the commandment of the Lord is pure.
It's pure.
Every word of God is pure.
It's what we read in the scriptures
and we find that he says here that it's pure.
And then notice he says enlightening the eyes,
giving insight, understanding.
And you begin to understand
as we look at this terminology here
and understand that the psalmist
is really elevating the scriptures
and understanding what he holds in his hand
and how precious it is.
And he says that the commandment of the Lord is pure,
enlightening the eyes.
He then says this in verse number nine,
it's kind of interesting in the context and the placement,
but he says the fear of the Lord is clean,
enduring forever.
You know, it's interesting,
he mentions about there in verse number nine
about the fear of the Lord is clean, enduring forever.
And obviously the scriptures
are not referred to as the fear of the Lord,
but I tell you,
the scriptures will help you have the fear of the Lord.
Amen.
You get into the law of the Lord,
the testimony of the Lord,
the statutes of the Lord,
the commandments of the Lord,
and you get into the Bible
and it will help you have a healthy fear of God.
We find that it says that in verse number nine,
that the fear of the Lord is clean, is clean.
And then it says this, notice, enduring forever.
I wonder this evening, how much do we fear the Lord?
I mentioned this morning about standing in awe of God.
You know what helps us stand in awe of God
is when we get into his word.
Begin to study the scriptures,
you begin to get a fresh glimpse of God,
high, holy, and lifted up.
It'll cause you to stand in awe of who he is.
Continues in verse number nine,
says the judgments of the Lord
are true and righteous altogether.
See, the scriptures not only contain the law,
the testimony, the statutes, the commandments,
but we find their judgments.
See, God is a just and righteous God.
And God has provided for us in his word,
the truth with regard to judgments
that would be meted upon individuals
because of their behavior.
There are consequences for your behavior.
We do not live in a bubble.
We do not operate in a bubble.
We understand that choices have consequences.
And we see that often.
We understand that there are times
in which we could look at the consequences
and say, I really don't want this.
We should think about that when you make the choice, right?
Because choices always have consequences.
And he says that the judgments of the Lord
are true and righteous altogether.
It's interesting as I look at these few verses of scripture
and think about how God is describing for us his word.
And I want you to think about the fact
that he says it's perfect, it's sure, it's right,
it's pure, it's true, and it's righteous.
Listen, I don't think, I submit to you this evening,
I don't think there's anything else on planet earth
that you can read that would fit that category.
Amen?
And you think about it, listen,
you then think about what it does,
that it converts the soul, it makes wise the simple,
it rejoices the heart, it enlightens the eyes.
Listen, that's what God tells us his word does.
So why in the world would we neglect reading the Bible?
See, I understand what the statistics are.
I understand this evening that many have given statistics
over the years about the low percentage of believers,
those that claim to go to church week after week
and that yet they've never read the Bible
in its entirety.
They do not read the Bible regularly.
There are some that have maybe felt pressure
because of that, so they'll read the Bible daily,
they'll read it regularly,
but they do it more out of rote religion, if you will.
Just kind of checking a box and making sure it's all done.
But I submit to you this evening that this is a living book.
And every time we open this book,
God wants to meet with us and God wants to talk to us.
God has a message for us and we get into the scriptures
and we allow the scriptures to get into us
and we begin to see what God is doing.
I'm mindful of what the Bible says in Philippians 4, 8
with regard to the things that we're to think on.
Man, the Bible fits all of that.
And oh, that we would spend so much time in his word
that we would begin to think and act biblically.
That just immediately what comes out of us as Bible,
the principles that God has given to us in his word.
We not only notice in the text
how the word of God is described,
but I want you to notice number two,
the word of God is desired.
It's desired by the psalmist,
but I would hope by each of us this evening as well.
Notice what the Bible says in verse number 10.
Notice that it says more to be desired are they.
What's he talking about?
All that he just explained to us, the scriptures.
More to be desired are they.
Notice the comparison than gold,
yea, then much fine gold.
You know people are chasing after gold,
desiring riches.
I mean, honestly, we understand where we live.
We understand our nation is a blessed nation
from a financial perspective.
We live in a very blessed area of our nation financially.
There are a lot of people that are seeking after
and desiring gold, riches.
People that will do all sorts of things
in order to gain more riches and more gold.
And here the Bible tells us that God's word
is to be desired by God's people more than gold or fine gold.
Can I tell you that gold is just something
that's temporary for us here on earth.
The Bible tells us that riches make wings
and they fly away, amen.
And we find here that the word of God,
it liveth and abideth forever.
And he says that it's to be desired.
Job said it this way in Job 23 in verse number 12.
And I always am fascinated by the testimony of Job
and the statement that he makes in this portion of scripture
with understanding all that he's gone through
and all that he's experienced.
But he says this,
neither have I gone back from the commandment of his lips.
I have esteemed the words of his mouth
more than my necessary food.
More than my necessary food.
For most of us, we don't skip too many meals.
Right?
Don't skip too many meals.
How's that work with skipping our Bible reading?
I mean, we ought never skip.
Listen, we become weak.
Amen?
We need the scriptures.
We need the Bible.
And we find that it says that there are more to be desired
than gold, yea, than much fine gold.
He doesn't just say yea than fine gold,
but he says yea than much, much, much fine gold.
Then notice the sweeter also than honey and the honeycomb.
Have you found that God's word is sweet?
You know, I've heard many times over the years,
I haven't heard it recently,
but there's times in which people will look at the Bible
and they'll say something like this
and they're being negative
and they'll refer to the Bible
as being a book that's just full of rules.
Do this and don't do that.
Listen, I hope this evening
that not one of us have that perspective.
It's just a poor perspective
because God's word is so much more
than a book of rules, of do's and don'ts.
Now, are there commandments contained
within the scriptures?
Absolutely.
But all of those commandments are there
given to us by a loving God
He understands that he's also just and therefore he wants us to know the truth so that we can obey and have his blessing.
That's amazing to me.
And we find here that God tells us that the Word of God is to be desired.
One of the verses that we memorized last month was 1 Peter 2 and verse number 2.
The Bible in that portion of scripture says,
Can I tell you this evening that as I begin to really meditate upon this
and think about this verse of scripture with regard to the Word of God being desired,
that as a newborn babe, I remember when I got saved.
I hope you remember when you got saved.
Before I got saved, I didn't read this book.
I didn't.
I never read it regularly.
I went to church for a few years before I got saved,
and I heard about reading the Bible and different things,
but I just never read it regularly.
But then I got saved.
The Spirit of God indwells you.
The Spirit of God is doing a work in you,
and all of a sudden I have this desire for the Bible.
And here's what I've learned as I go through life and my own personal experience
understanding this truth with regard to desire here in this text of scripture,
that as newborn babes desire the sincere milk of the Word,
that ye may grow thereby, and if you learn to desire it as a babe,
you'll continue to desire it as you grow in your faith.
Amen?
You know what I've learned?
I just turned 46 last month.
I still like to eat.
How many of you like to eat?
Right?
You got a desire for food when you were a babe.
But didn't that desire grow?
Right?
You ate this afternoon.
How many of you ate this afternoon?
You're going to go home tonight and eat something.
Right?
You desire it.
And I'm just wondering this evening as we think about that
and begin to make the correlations that God gives us with analogies in His Word,
how much do we desire the Bible?
Because He says that the Word of God is desired.
More to be desired are they than gold, yea, than much fine gold,
sweeter also than the honey and the honeycomb.
Strong meat.
I'm thankful for meat.
Amen?
I'm thankful I don't have a milk diet anymore.
Praise the Lord.
I don't know the last time I had milk, but I know when I had meat last.
Amen?
And I like meat.
The Bible talks about the meat of the Word.
Strong meat belonging to them that are full age.
You begin to understand the desire,
and I wonder this evening as we look at this portion of Scripture
and begin to understand the description,
but also how God's Word is desired.
And then we notice number three,
and I want you to really as we get through the end of this text,
and I'm going to try to get quickly.
I know we have a business meeting this evening,
but I want you to notice number three.
The Word of God is our defense.
It's our defense.
Notice in verse number 11,
the Bible says,
Moreover, by them.
And then notice this phrase is thy servant warned.
Now, generally speaking,
are warnings good things or bad things?
Good things.
Amen?
You get a warning, bridge out ahead.
I mean, it's probably a pretty good thing
that somebody let you know the bridge was out.
There's warning labels on different products.
If you have some type of allergen,
they have warnings on different packages of foods.
Why?
To help you avoid some type of issue medically
because of consuming something that you were allergic to.
Chemicals, cleaning supplies, warnings, warnings, warnings.
I always think it's funny that on my coffee,
it says warning contents are hot.
They should be.
But for some reason, they have to put the warning on there.
And we see that warnings, generally speaking,
they're good things.
And here, I would submit to you that as we look at the Scriptures
and we see what God is telling us,
that moreover by them, by the Scriptures,
is thy servant warned.
He then says this,
And in keeping of them there is great reward.
The warning that God gives us in His Word
of what not to do, of what to avoid,
and helping us to live a life that's pleasing in His sight.
And when we take heed to the warning,
as we take and examine the Scriptures
and we take heed to the warning,
then what happens is we're spared.
We're spared the consequences
of whatever that behavior could lead to.
And He says,
Moreover by them is thy servant warned,
and in keeping of them there is great reward.
I'm thankful that our God
has given to us the principle in His Word
of obedience leads to blessing.
Now understand with me this evening
that as God's people,
it should not be that we're simply seeking a blessing.
We're seeking the Lord.
It's about my fellowship with God.
It's about the fact that I have the opportunity to be in His presence.
I'm not just looking for the blessing,
but the one who gives the blessing.
Does that make sense?
And sometimes we can get so caught up in the blessing
and maybe enjoying the blessing
that we might forget the one who gave us the blessing.
But He says,
In keeping of them there is great reward.
Listen, I would submit to you this evening
that in my Christian life
that I have had the privilege
of reading the Bible through and through
and I've not always obeyed.
I've not always followed exactly what the scriptures have said.
But in the times that I have,
I have avoided some really terrible pitfalls.
And I've received some wonderful blessings
in obeying the Word of God.
And praise God for it.
It's our defense.
I want you to notice as we begin to look at verse 12 and 13,
He says there's kind of this progression
that goes here in verses 12 and 13.
He says,
Who can understand His errors?
I want you to see that word errors.
And then He says in the latter part of the verse,
Cleanse now me from,
notice what He says,
secret faults.
Secret faults.
So you see this progression from errors to secret faults.
Listen, the reality this evening
is that you're probably thankful just as I am
that all of your faults are not known for all humanity.
Amen.
Sometimes we read the scriptures
and we criticize some characters,
some Bible heroes, if you will,
that have gone before us
and were quick to criticize some of their behavior.
And I've often thought,
I'm sure glad that God's not writing all my life story down
and letting thousands, millions upon millions of people
reading it for however long of human history.
Amen.
Peter sunk.
I understand.
But he walked further than you did.
And anyone else that was in the boat.
He's the only one that got out.
Amen.
And we see here that this progression,
listen, I just want you to know this evening
that when we look here and we see the heart of the psalmist
and we think about the word of God as our defense
and He says who can understand His errors,
listen, Paul says it this way,
I would not know sin except for the law.
I wouldn't know that I was guilty of covetousness
unless the law said thou shalt not covet.
Amen.
And so we find here that he says who can understand His errors.
It's through a proper relationship with God and His word
that we understand what sin is.
It's that we understand the error of our way.
And he says, cleanse now me from secret faults.
What a wonderful perspective that the psalmist has here
of this cleansing, of this cleaning.
And we understand, and I've said it before,
it's not about being cleaner, it's about being clean.
There's a difference between being clean and being cleaner.
You can have something that's really dirty
and you can rinse it out.
It's cleaner than it was, but it's not clean.
I've used the illustration before.
You get a dirty fork when you go out to the restaurant
and you say there's something crusty on here.
Listen, I don't want that waiter to just take out a little handkerchief
and just kind of, here you go, man, it's all off of there.
I don't want that fork. Do you?
No way, man. I want a clean fork.
We're to be clean.
He says, cleanse thou me from secret faults.
Let me ask you this tonight.
Who knows about the secret faults?
God and the psalmist.
You know your secret faults. Amen?
No one else may know your secret faults,
but you do and God does.
I used the illustration this morning of Rachel
and the illustration of Achan.
You know and God knows.
You cannot hide anything from God.
You may think it's a secret, but it's known by you
and it's known by God.
He says errors, he says secret faults.
Notice in verse number 13, he says,
keep back thy servant also from presumptuous sins.
This is the idea of deliberate violations.
Right? It's like the kid that knows he shouldn't do it,
but he does it anyway.
Juliana, the other day, she called me.
She said, I told him not to do it
and he looked right at me and he did it anyway.
That little sinner. Amen?
And the reality is that you understand presumptuous sins.
Listen, even as adult people, as Christians,
there are times that we know
that we ought not do something and we do it anyway.
It's gonna make me feel good.
I really just need to give them a piece of my mind. I really just need to say
this one thing.
Don't sin. Don't sin.
He says, keep back thy servant also from presumptuous sins.
Let them, the presumptuous sins, not have dominion
over me. Listen, as believers
according to Romans 6, we have been delivered from the power of sin.
I'm no longer, if you're saved here this evening, you're no longer in bondage to sin.
And he tells us, talking about liberty in the book of Galatians, you can read in
chapter 5, you can read
also as Peter talks about it with the false teachers and false prophets there,
the reality is that we are not to be entangled again
in bondage. I've been delivered.
And so he says, listen, he says, let them not have dominion
over me. Sin is a trap.
It's a trap. You start getting, you know, we've talked about a web of lies, you've
shared the illustration with your children, no doubt at some point if you
have kids,
you tell one lie and then you gotta tell another lie to cover up that lie, and then you gotta tell another lie,
and then you don't know what you told that person and this person, and you're all kinds of,
and it's a mess. Begins to have dominion.
He says, he says, let them not have dominion over me,
then shall I be upright, and notice this,
and I shall be innocent from the great
transgression. Oh, that God would keep us in a place
that that great transgression doesn't happen in your life or in my life.
We begin to think about this
cycle here, this pattern here, where he talks about this,
these errors, the secret faults, the presumptuous sins, the great
transgression.
There's a progression. I said that this morning.
The children of Israel didn't just go out and sacrifice their kids to Molech on day one.
They were told when they landed in the land not to
do after the Egyptians and the land that they left and not to do after the
inhabitants of the land.
They're God's people, and God said you're to live my way.
We find that the nations of the
the peoples that indwelled in the land, they had influence and they began to
do some of the same very things that those people were guilty of by the way
that God judged them for their own sin.
I want you to see the prayer of consecration in verse number 14.
He says, let the words of my mouth
and the meditation of my heart be acceptable
in thy sight. Oh Lord, my strength
and my Redeemer. Can I tell you this evening that your words are important,
the words of our mouth. But I really want to focus on that second thing when he says
the meditation
of my heart. I mentioned this morning there's a great battle for your mind and
for mine.
He says that we're to renew our mind. We're to bring into captivity every thought to
the obedience of Christ.
We understand as we look here at this prayer of consecration, he says in the
meditation
of my heart, be careful what you think about because before long you'll be doing it.
Thoughts become actions.
It's so imperative that we see that in these verses of scripture we're reminded
that the Word of God
is our defense. I understand the Lord is my defense but
God's Word as we look here at this text and we see
what God's Word does for us and how it helps us in this area.
I preached this morning, awake to righteousness and sin not.
The more I get alone with the Lord, the more I get into his Word.
This Word will keep me, this book will keep me from sin.
And I want you to look at two passages and we'll be done this evening. I want you to look
in Deuteronomy chapter 17.
Deuteronomy chapter 17 is a passage of scripture that is written
as they're preparing to go into the land that God had prepared for them.
We find that in the text of scripture that God is speaking about
kings. I do not believe that it was ever God's
purpose for his people to have kings. It was a theocracy and God determined that it
would be that way but we understand that
after the period of the judges and all that was taking place there, they desired a king.
They wanted to be like the other lands. They had this desire, these other
people groups and so God knowing had provided some instruction here
in Deuteronomy 17 with regard to when you have a king. I was said a king over
me and verse 14 says that but I want you to notice
what God tells us in verse 18 and 19 with regard to this thought tonight that
the Word of God is our defense. Notice what it says.
And it shall be in verse 18 of Deuteronomy 17 and it shall be
when he sitteth upon the throne of his kingdom.
Notice what it says that he shall write him
a copy of this law in a book out of that which is before the priest and
Levites. I don't know if you've ever tried to
write down a lot of scripture
but if you think about the content here and you think about the first
five books, you sit down and you write all of that out.
There's something about learning that when you hear it but you also write it,
it's more impactful. And he says here that the king
and I notice as I look at it, it doesn't say that he shall have someone write a
copy for him. Right? Is that what your Bible says? No,
no. It says that he shall write him a copy. I don't have
time. I understand it's a long process. I mean I'll challenge you. Go ahead and
sit down this week and write out the book of Genesis
so you can have a copy of it.
Look at verse 19 and it shall be with him
and he shall read there in all the days of his life
that he may learn to fear the Lord his God
to keep all the words of this law in these statutes
to do them. That his heart be not lifted up above his brethren and that he turn
not aside from the commandment to the right hand or to the left
to the end that he may prolong his days in his kingdom
he and his children in the midst of Israel. I would tell you this evening
that it would have been really good for a lot
of the kings if they had followed this instruction.
Amen? You would read the book of first and second kings, the book of first and
second chronicles and many of the prophets.
You would read them different than you do today
if they had taken this admonition, this charge, this commandment and fulfilled it.
Notice what it does. It says that it shall be with him and he's gonna
read it all the days of his life so he could do what? He may learn the
fear of the Lord. You remember we saw that in verse number nine of our text
of scripture in Psalm 19 and he says that he's gonna
learn them, he's gonna do them, he's gonna keep them.
He says that his heart be not lifted up. Listen, pride is a dangerous thing.
Pride is destructive. Only by pride cometh contention.
Amen? The bible says that God resisteth the proud
but gives grace to the humble. God hates pride
and God knows how to abase us and he says that his heart be not lifted up. You
know how you stay humble? You stay in this book. I'm telling you
there's nothing like this book that will keep you humble.
You know why? Because you understand who you are and who God is.
Paul said in Acts 20 that he was going to serve the Lord in all humility,
in all humility in Acts 20. How do we have that humility? It comes from that
that proper relationship to the word of God. It's our defense. Notice in Joshua 1
and I'll close with this in Joshua 1. Notice what the bible says in Joshua 1.
It's a familiar verse of scripture.
Joshua's gonna have the responsibility to go and really take the mantle if you
will and lead the children of Israel into the land of promise and
Moses is dead and God is going to encourage
Joshua for the task at hand. Not only does God tell Joshua I'm going
to be with you and by the way that's encouraging is it not?
Joshua here's what I have for you and I'm going to be with you.
Praise God. But I want you to notice what God tells Joshua in verse number
eight. This book of the law
shall not depart out of thy mouth but thou shalt meditate therein day and
night. Why? That thou mayest observe to do
according to all that is written therein.
All that is written therein. He says for then thou shalt make thy way
prosperous and then thou shalt have good
success. I believe this evening that every child of God wants
the then. We want then. We want to have our way
prosperous and we want to have good success
but then comes after the action of what we read in the beginning
portion of verse eight that we're not allowing the law to depart
out of our mouth that we're meditating in day and night that we're observing to
do according to all that is written therein and it's
absolutely imperative this evening that we
you're saying the Word of God is our defense. Listen, I know I quoted it this morning and
I think it was D.L. Moody that said, this book will keep you from sin or sin will keep
you from this book. I ask you tonight, we started out by talking about being Baptist
and having a Bible and saying the Bible is our sole authority for faith and practice
and it is. We sing about the B-I-B-L-E, it's the book for me. But you can be in the right
kind of church, you can have the right kind of Bible, you can sing about it, you can rejoice
to have it, but the reality is that you can have all of those things and yet not spend
time in God's Word. You have the right book. You know it's God's Word, you know it's inerrant,
you know it's perfect, you know what it can do, but you just, you're too busy. Too many
things going on. You know, that's what the devil wants to do, he wants to keep us busy.
He wants to keep us busy. And then what happens? I get separated from God's Word and God's
Word is my defense. And all of a sudden, I'm busy and I don't have, I can't, and I can't,
we make time to eat, we make time to grab something on the go, whatever it is, because
I need that physical sustenance. We need the spiritual sustenance. We need God's Word.
The law of the Lord. I hope that you'd meditate upon that passage this week and just understand
what God's Word is and what it will do for you. And if you don't have that regular time
with the Lord, commit to God. God, I need this. I need this. And see what God will do
in and through your life. Let's pray. Father, we love you. Thank you for loving us. God,
I thank you for the Bible. Lord, I pray that you'd help us to be people of the book, not
just in word but in deed. I pray that in the time of invitation this evening that you would
work. Lord, help us to respond. Help us, Lord, to make commitments to thee. Help us to truly
examine our own lives with regard to our relationship to your Word. We're to know you. I can only
know you through your Word. I pray that you'd have your will and way if it's in Christ and
we pray. Kimberly's going to play quietly on the piano. If you'd stand with me as she
plays the altar is open.